<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Oleg's Web Log - Security Architecting</title><link href="http://www.wryway.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.wryway.com/feeds/security-architecting.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.wryway.com/</id><updated>2017-12-25T19:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Should an authenticator be paired with an identificator?</title><link href="http://www.wryway.com/blog/pairing-of-authenticator-with-identificator/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-25T19:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-25T19:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Oleg Mitrofanov</name></author><id>tag:www.wryway.com,2017-12-25:/blog/pairing-of-authenticator-with-identificator/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Or can they not?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It seamed reasonable when I heard that it was a good security practice to pair
an authenticator with an identificator. I could not give a concrete explanation
of why it should be so. This post is an attempt to provide such explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Definitions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, let's agree on a few terms: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Authenticator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a secret (or a set of public and secret components) used
to prove caller's identity or knoweldge of a secret. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Identificator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a non-secret reference to the authenticator used to state
caller's identity or secret id. It can be a reference to an identity (e.g.
username) or a secret specific reference (e.g. API Key Id).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Examples&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few instances of identificators and authenticators to make it tangible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identificator &amp;amp; authenticator pair examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Username &amp;amp; Password&lt;/em&gt;, where  username, the identificator, is a reference to
user's identity; password is the authenticator. Used in client-to-server and
rarely server-to-server authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;API Key Id &amp;amp; API Secret Key&lt;/em&gt; , where API Key Id, the identificator, is a
reference to the API Secret Key (authenticator); a user can have more than one
pair of these. Used in client-to-server and server-to-server authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Host name &amp;amp; server TLS certificate&lt;/em&gt;. Used in server-to-client
authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sender email address &amp;amp; sender's private-public key pair&lt;/em&gt;, where the email
address is the identificator, and the key pair is the authenticator. Used in
client-to-client authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identificator-less authenticator (or is it authenticator-less identificator?)
examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monolithic API Key not broken into Key Id and Key Secret&lt;/em&gt;. E.g. &lt;a href="https://developer.nytimes.com/signup"&gt;NY Times API
 Key&lt;/a&gt; currently looks like a UUID with
removed dashes: &lt;em&gt;4dd3f7b027074ff89961cfa321a2dfd2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of an identificator misuse:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;SSN&lt;/em&gt; – is a number that in the US uniquely identifies US citizens and
residents (something that would not be possible using first and last name
combination for they are not unique across population). As a low-entropy number
and because of its identification role it should clearly not be a secret.
However, practically, many private and government establishments treat it as a
secret and use to authenticate a person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;So why should they come in pair?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After thinking on the subject for a while I came up with the following list of
issues arising from an authenticator  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; being paired with an
identificator. The first three apply to client-to-server and server-to-server
authentication. The fourth and fifth apply to the server-to-client and
client-to-client authentication:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The authenticator cannot be stored securely in the back end using traditional
hashing with a salt approach. If all authenticators are stored hashed with as
salt (as they should be) but without any identificators to reference them, then
the authenticating party will have to hash the authenticator with all available
salts prior to being able to authenticate. The authentication will be slowing
down for all callers as their number grows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every new authenticator issued will be increasing attacker's chances of
recovering a valid authenticator and compromise one of the callers. For
example, if you randomly generate 128-bit long authenticators, and issue only 1
authenticator, it'll take an attacker 2&lt;sup&gt;128&lt;/sup&gt;/2=2&lt;sup&gt;127&lt;/sup&gt; time on
average to recover it by brute forcing the available key space. With 1024 active
authenticators the time to recover a valid key will be decreased to
2&lt;sup&gt;127&lt;/sup&gt;/2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;=2&lt;sup&gt;117&lt;/sup&gt;. With 32768 active
authenticators, the time goes down to 2&lt;sup&gt;112&lt;/sup&gt;. To be equally secure an
authenticator will be required to employ more bits (become longer) compared to
the case where it is accompanied by an identificator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In case of non-local communication channel, the authenticator or a temporary
token generated from it will have to be transmitted on the wire with every
authenticated call. This is how web authentication works today, which is deemed
acceptable. However, if paired with an identificator, the security bar can be
raised for authenticated calls by employing HMAC signing where the authenticator
is not sent over the wire at all (this is how AWS SigV4 works).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The authenticating party may not be capable of storing authenticators for all
callers and rely on the presence of an identificator to be able to retrieve
artifacts required to authenticate the caller. This is the case of
client-to-client authentication between an email sender and receiver, where the
receiver may have to retrieve sender's public key before they can authenticate
the message. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It may be required for the authenticating party to only communicate to a
particular party with a valid authenticator, and not to any party with a
valid authenticator. This may not matter for client-to-server authentication,
but is the case for the server-to-client HTTPS authentication where the web
server has to prove its identity to the user agent.  Had a server certificate
only contained a validly signed public key, without hostname, it would not have
been possible for the user agent to be convinced that the certificate was issued
for the web site it was trying to talk to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After staring at the above list for a bit, I challenged myself to think about
how identificator-less authenticators can be stored securely.  The following
section contains a couple of potential solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Can identificator-less authenticators be stored securely?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple solution to storing identificator-less authenticators securely is to
treat the first part of the authenticator as an identificator and the second
part as the actual secret. When storing them only the second part will be
hashed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another solution is, at the expense of introduction of an extra secret and
having to manage it, to synthetically generate identificators from the
authenticators using a secret salt. I do not see any apparent high-risk issues
with this solution, however, it was not reviewed by crypto experts and can
potentially be horribly broken. The back-end data store table can look as
follows when this scheme is employed (where &lt;code&gt;SSalt&lt;/code&gt; is short for &lt;code&gt;SecretSalt&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;| Identificator                                | Hashed Authenticator               |
| SSaltVersion$SlowHash(SSalt, Authenticator)  | Salt$SlowHash(Salt, Authenticator) |
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the threats to this approach is once the secret salt and the list of
identificators are leaked, all authenticators hashed with that secret salt
version will be compromised. This is as opposed to a leaked list of
authenticator hashes where an attacker will have to spend considerable effort to
recover each authenticator. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Authentication"></category></entry></feed>